John Allman Papers
John Allman Papers
1964-2017
Allman, John, 1935-
2.75 linear ft.
America poet; correspondence, submission files, drafts, audio and videorecordings
2463714
Biographical History
John Allman (1935- ) is an award-winning American poet.
Born in New York City, Allman holds a B.A. from Hunter College and an M.A. from Syracuse University in creative writing. He taught at Cazenovia College in Central New York State and, for 26 years, at Rockland Community College of the State University of New York. He is retired and lives in Katonah, NY, with his wife, Eileen Allman, also a writer.
His awards include the Helen Bulls Prize from Poetry Northwest (1976) and a Pushcart Poetry Prize (1983); in 1984 and 1990, he was awarded National Endowment for the Arts Creative Writing Fellowships in Poetry. Journals that have published John Allman's poems include The Yale Review, North Dakota Quarterly, Kestrel, The Antioch Review, The Paris Review, and Atlantic Monthly, as well as online journals Full Circle and Blackbird.
He is the author of six books of poetry: Walking Four Ways in the Wind (1979); Clio's Children (1985), Scenarios for a Mixed Landscape (1986), Curve Away from Stillness (1989), Inhabited World: New & Selected Poems 1970-1995 (1995), and Loew's Triboro (2004). He is also the author of a collection of fiction, Descending Fire & Other Stories (1994).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Allman Papers contains correspondence files, memorabilia printed material, records pertaining to his work, writings, and a small amount of miscellany.
Correspondence-subject files contains a mix of incoming and outgoing correspondence with friends, colleagues, editors, and publishers. Notable correspondents include poets Philip Booth and Jay Meek. The most extensive correspondence is with Anna Munster, a physician in Pearl River, New York. Munster and Allman were evidently good friends; the letters, which include both incoming and outgoing, are affectionate, detailed, and often include enclosures of brief poems or pieces of writing by Munster or Allman. In some cases, Allman had written notes about the person on the front of the folder in which the items were donated; these have been preserved and are foldered with the relevant correspondence.
Memorabilia consists of clippings about Allman from various publications, photographs of Allman, and two portraits of him, one by his wife.
The bulk of Printed material consists of reviews of Allman's published collections of poetry. Also in this series are advertisements or announcements of appearances (e.g. lectures, workshops, panel discussions, etc.), a copy of his entry in Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series, Vol. 15, and a few clippings by or about other poets.
Records contains logs of poetry and short stories along with lists and correspondence relating to submissions of Allman's work to a wide range of publications, including The New Yorker and Atlantic Monthly.
Writings contains both prose and poetry works, as well as a few speeches and miscellaneous items. Types of material include typescripts with and without annotations, galleys, proofs, and so on. In some cases, Allman had written notes on the front of the folder in which the items were donated; these have been preserved and are foldered with the relevant items.
Miscellany consists of audio recordings and videorecordings. Included here are several audio recordings of Allman reading his poetry, and a video recording of a recital at Juilliard for which the performer set some of Allman's poems to music.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by topic or title. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name and within that chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Allman, John, 1935-; Booth, Philip E.; Laughlin, James, 1914-; Mairowitz, David Zane, 1943-; Meek, Jay.; Munster, Anna J.; Slate, Ron.; New Directions Publishing Corp.; American poetry.; Poets -- Correspondence.; Poets, American.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Interviews.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; VHS.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.; Authors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Allman, 2006-2013.
Accruals
Additional material arrives irregularly from donor.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Allman's notes on selected correspondence (Box 1)
  - Allen, Richard (Dick), 1987-1988; 2009 (Box 1)
  - Associated Writing Programs Series for Contemporary Poets, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1978-1979; undated (Box 1)
  - Becker, Margot, 1988; 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Booth, Philip, 1979; 1985,; 1989,; 1995 (Box 1)
  - The Chowder Review, 1977-1982; undated; Ron Slate (Box 1)
  - Duemer, Joe, 1990-1994; includes essay by Allman on Wallace Stevens (Box 1)
  - Epos, circa 1972-1074; Evelyn Thorne (Box 1)
  - Glassgold, Peter, See New Directions Press.
  - Gurko, Leo, 1990; 1994,; 1996,; 2006 (Box 1)
  - Heyen, William (Bill), 1991; 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Ironwood, 1985-1986; Michael Cuddihy (Box 1)
  - Kessler, Milton, 1991; 1996 (Box 1)
  - Laughlin, James, 1984-1995; 1997; editor at New Directions Press (Box 1)
  - Lummis, Suzanne, 2006; includes some of her poems (Box 1)
  - Mairowitz, David Zane, 1987-1992; 1994-1997,; 2002-2006; fellow student at Hunter College (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Review, 1978-1991; Bill Page, Paul Jenkins (Box 1)
  - Meek, Jay, 1987-2002; fellow student in graduate writing program at Syracuse University (Box 1)
  - Munster, Anna J., 1996-1998; enclosed with many of the letters are Munster's poems, essays, etc.; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Munster, Anna J., 1999-2009; undated; undated material includes a science fiction short story, some poems, and a poem by her granddaughter Miranda; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - New Directions Press, 1984-1985; 1987,; 1992-1998; Peter Glassgold, James Laughlin (Box 2)
    See also Laughlin, James.
  - Poetry Northwest, undated; David Wagoner (Box 2)
  - The Quarterly, circa 1986-1998; includes typescripts of several poems with annotations/corrections; Gordon Lish (Box 2)
  - San Diego State University, circa 1988; rights to a poem (Box 2)
  - Serio, John, 1995; concerns Allman's collection Inhabited World; includes proofs with different fonts, final page proofs, etc. (Box 2)
  - Slate, Ron, See The Chowder Review.
  - Syracuse University, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, mix of incoming and outgoing (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - 50th birthday, 1985; invitation; commemorative poem by Peter Dee (Box 2)
  - Clippings about, 1977-2005; undated (Box 2)
  - "Photos by Saul White", 1984 (Box 2)
  - "Photos of John Allman and Dan Masterson, Writer's Voice series, West Side YMCA", 2004 (Box 2)
  - Photos, miscellaneous, 1977; 1994 (Box 2)
  - Portrait of John Allman by Eileen Allman, circa 1973; color reproduction (Box 2)
  - Sketch of John Allman Joan Silberman, 1985; original art (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - Appearances, 1977-1999; undated; fliers, posters, announcements, and other items regarding appearances, lectures, workshops, panels, etc. (Box 2)
  - Article "John Allman," from Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series, Vol. 15, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1977; 1979; articles on or by other poets (Box 2)
  - Reviews, Clio's Children, 1985; includes letter to unidentified editor from Allman; New Directions book information sheet; two page statement by Allman on aims and methods of the book (Box 2)
  - Reviews, Curve Away from Stillness, 1989; includes proof of New Directions ad; lengthy essay from Parnassus Poetry in Review (Box 2)
  - Reviews, Descending Fire and Other Stories, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Reviews, Inhabited World, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Reviews, Scenarios for a Mixed Landscape, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Reviews, Walking Four Ways in the Wind, 1979 (Box 3)
- Records
  - Bibliography of works published, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Log of poems and short stories, 2006; bound volume; title page reads, "Log of poems started and completed 1973-1990 and log of a few short stories Dec 14, 2006 JA" (Box 3)
  - Submission lists, 1966-1994; lists of poems, when and to whom submitted, responses (Box 3)
  - Submissions, 1967-1993; correspondence from editors and publishers relating to submissions, organized chronologically; 2 folders (Box 3)
    See also specific publishers under Correspondence-subject files, e.g. New Directions Press.
- Writings
  For reviews of Allman's work, see Printed material: Reviews.
  - Poetry
    - The Blue Gazebo, typescript; two slightly different versions, donated at different times; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Curve Away from Stillness, 1988; afterword only, by Peter Coleman (Box 3)
    - Deep Breath: New and Selected Poems 2004-2017 (Box 6)
    - Elegies and dreams: a chapbook, typescript with annotations (Box 3)
    - Older Than Our Fathers, two slightly different versions, donated at different times (Box 3)
    - Older Than Our Fathers, Mudlark No. 37, 2008; includes correspondence with editor, photos, drafts with corrections, printout of final version as posted online (Box 3)
    - Inhabited World, See Correspondence-subject files: Serio, John.
    - Scenarios for a Mixed Landscape, "original draft"; typescript with corrections (Box 3)
    - Something Rather Than Nothing, 2012-2013 (Box 4)
    - Walking Four Ways in the Wind (original title: Filling the Straight), 1979-1980; galleys, page proofs; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Uncollected or unpublished", 1970-1971; 1974-1990; marked by the donor as such when donated, but may have been published since (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous drafts of individual poems (Box 4)
  - Prose
    - The Daughters of Lazarus (novel), 1997; "penultimate draft"; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Essays, graduate school, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - A Fine Romance: Stories, handwritten date of 2009 on title page (Box 4)
    - A Fine Romance: Stories, handwritten "copyright 2007" on title page (Box 5)
  - Speeches, lectures
    - "On Judith Johnson's Uranium Poems and Impossible Buildings and their connection to her later work", 2007; AWP conference paper on Judith Johnson; drafts, notes (Box 5)
    - "Poetry and memory," Foust Lecture, Kutztown University, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "About poetry", undated; several copies, some with annotations (Box 5)
    - "Notes", undated; appears to be semi-humorous personal statement/autobiographical sketch (Box 5)
    - Clippings of some of Allman's poetry, undated (Box 5)
- Miscellany
  - Interview, "Jack 1985 / 1984", allman_001; 1 VHS tape (Box 5)
  - Interview, "Here We Are", 1985; allman_002; 1 VHS tape (Box 5)
  - Recital, "Eric Ewazen Recital / Juilliard / 2/5/94 / Scenarios for a mixed landscape", 5 Feb 1994 [?]; allman_003; Allman's poems set to music, includes program listing items; two different dates are written on the item (Box 5)
  - Allman reading, 1980; undated; allman_004, allman_005, allman_006; audio recordings of Allman reading his poetry; 3 audiocassettes (Box 5)